thank you
what is a relinquishment in giving up
what do you need to give up why
what does it mean
why is it necessary
so what what practically what are the
things you have to give up
did you actually step two
try and relinquish for sake
trying to manage the suffering
okay so if you're not trying to manage
suffering but you still live with your
spouse children can you keep that and then give
children can you keep that and then give
up management and behind enlightened
freaking suffering probably not so there
are certain things you have to give up
give up
so where is the line with the things you
have to give up give up
maybe you should try to understand what
things you don't truly need or you can
live without them and then yeah it's a
good game basically re-evaluate like
what is necessary to have
what isn't and then start there but
obviously sometimes
that can result not that specifically
but people can have a view in regards to
that whereby they think okay so if I
give everything up I'll be free
so that they don't use any discernment
or Reason to see where the line is
and just start throwing everything away
so to speak
and yeah that might result in a very
simple life but fundamentally you cannot
do that with your own body and your own
senses and that's what the problem is
you can't just just discard like you can
items that you possess
so that needs to be understood while it
is still there so while you still have
it you need to understand how
how you can not have it really without
destroying it without blaming the eyes
or ears for hearing or seeing and so on
if I click something I should give it up
so for example if I should give up my
likes yes whatever food is my preference
for example I should stop eating bad
food instead of a valid
instead of a valid
is it
no no because
that's not what the problem is the
problem is not this something is
agreeable to you
because you so if things are
the problem is that you can't see the
line between something being agreeable
and you needing to have it and needing
to keep it and wanting it or being
enslaved by it or being dependent on it
so just because something is agreeable
to you that you have a preference for
something doesn't mean you have to
relinquish it but what if you're
emotionally attached to it
what if you really you're going to be
miserable if you don't get what you like
should you give it up then
so sometimes I think yes it can it can
help but then there's a obviously a
limit to that like you can't give up all
food because you can't just because you
can't stop
having some kind of desire in regard to
food but would it be okay that somebody
gives up only food that they like and
only stuff that they don't like
would that result in in
growing their mind and
no why not
because it's still acting out of legs
but just denying just doing the opposite
right but they're not feeding their
likes anymore they're not eating the
stuff they like they're only the stuff
that they don't like yes but they're
acting out of the same thing which thing
preference I'm just turning it the other way the
I'm just turning it the other way the
the preference towards the liking food
the test oh sure and what else is a
problem there
believe that the problem is the exactly
yeah yeah your preference your like your
emotional dependence was not in the
taste so yes there is a practical line there
so yes there is a practical line there
as in
if you are if you have no perspective
then yeah maybe give it up like don't
eat that just to see whether your mind
will be disturbing how much
but fundamentally yeah that is not where
the problem is the problem is in the
desire and lust that's infecting your
thoughts not the sense objects
and that's where the uh Protein that's
where the true relinquishment happens
but in order to even
kind of comprehend that direction yeah
some practical physical relinquishment
needs to be done needs to be actually
performed so yeah the references of course the
so yeah the references of course the
precepts things you would give up
through the precepts
um and then further than that yeah you
can you know everybody can get really
inspired with the idea of your still
life and then just start throwing
everything out but
now that can become an issue you might
be just acting out of a view that
implies that problem was in these things
not in my desire and lust on the mental
level uh but if on the other hand you use some
uh but if on the other hand you use some
practical kind of reasoning I said well
do I really need this can I live without
it
certainly it's better to be less
cluttered certain it's better to go in
the direction of relinquishment and
simplification but and then then fine
then if you decide the things can be
dismissed given up given away that's
that's all right but you can still keep
the perspective that the the problem is
actually fundamentally on the level of
the the mind taking up those things the
mind taking up the uh
the the preferences with lust leaning
towards them with last twitterversion
and so on
what kind of relinquishment then because
the suit is so basically the
pretty much the prerequisite
for establishing your mind and dwelling
in Jannah is the complete relinquishment
and even the like even Sati katana
which is generally the practice of
mindfulness presupposes
um overcoming happiness and concerns in
regard to the entire world and then you
can dwell mindfully
so that's also a form of relinquishment
to what extent
I mean I don't need to also understand I
just said it the entire world but what
would be the
okay enough
enough
what would be the Practical examples of
giving up and overcoming
happiness and relinquishment in regard
to the entire world so you keep the
precepts you're not engaging with
centrality but there is still obviously
more to the world
what are the other things you have to
give up
practically not just metaphorically
not just metaphorically
in order to be able to surmount the
world to surmount the concern regarding
the world in order to be able to dwell
correctly mindful in order to experience
their voice talk about that then you are
truly detached from the realm of
thinking and pondering the mind is
withdrawn from it and that is the first
John what are those things you have to give
what are those things you have to give
up
it's obviously core centrality core seal
will chore Indulgence in food of course
company of course but
what else now
there's more to that obviously
maybe it's um you know the Indulgence in
thought I'd say they could
to
put too much
value on sort of arranging things
if you see that that this ultimately is
futile and I mean and recognizing that
as a hindrance
um even like arranging things on the
level of the thought yes sort of
controlling it or making it whatever
yeah sort of yeah quiet quietness
uh yeah but see the problem with that
could be that somebody can do that
before they got The Right View
so they're quieting their mind down
with ignorance so they still don't know
the Escape but they start valuing the
non-disturbance but seeking the practice is disturbing
but seeking the practice is disturbing
but it's a good type of disturbance
because it can result in the Right View
that can then result in public
Liberation that was the we spoke about
it relatively often there
when somebody and even the Buddha
himself said in that the two types of
thought like you you would first realize
how the problem is the unwholesome
thoughts not thought in itself
then you put them into two categories
anything that's great version delusion
he would not engage with anything that's
great a non-grid another version of
delusion he would allow and we create a
version illusion present himself he
would not like trying to get rid of it
get rid of it but he would just remind
himself of the context of The Petal of
the danger of her little satisfaction
how this is intending for his harm for
harm of others for harm of all then
those thoughts would subside on their
own and that was his practice and that was
and that was his practice and that was
not peaceful that was still work there
was still burden obviously on the right
level of enduring these thoughts
pressuring you not acting out and then
re-establishing the context in regard to
them until they subside
when he fully developed that
completely sort of when all he had was
the good non-green non-aversion
non-delusion he was still maintaining the context and
he was still maintaining the context and
then he realized oh but yeah I don't
need to do this now because these
thoughts are not harmful so what if I
just don't let them be
oh and by the way that was that
difference in that um
in Pali it doesn't really he just goes
into second genre but this explains how
he was first intentionally involved with
maintaining the context and doing that
Bhavan in regard to the unwholesome
states until they subside
then after that when he had wholesome
States endure he realized I don't need
to be intentionally involved with this
context constantly because these
thoughts are not contradicting it not
going against it and then he or what if
I allow these thinking and pondering
basically to be and instead just unify
my mind internally on the basis of this
wholesome environment that I have worked
for and then he entered the first John
and then he entered the first John
and then furthermore then goes into
second so that is like missing step I
was talking about that you wouldn't find
in the palace so that's the point so
like um yes you shouldn't be or like you know
um yes you shouldn't be or like you know
if somebody is trying to control the
thoughts to make any plan yeah you you
gotta recognize that
it's not going to lead to a solution but
at the same time thoughts are not a
problem first genre is thinking and
pondering entirely
and it's the peaceful Sublime abiding
that's sufficient for when the mind is
uh totally withdrawn from it uh so the
problem is that whether they're still
solute in Greater version delusion
distraction cruelty and so on and those
are now subtle things that I was leading
to by asking what are the other less
subtle things you need to give up before
you can start Discerning these roots of
your thoughts
in regard to the world so given that
core centrality is gone
you know cruelty acting out of anger is
gone what are the things that are not gone
what are the things that are not gone
there's worldly came renowned status
position okay so basically kind of
your relationship with others
connections comparisons
gone well I was going to suggest that it
would then come down to the level of
views relinquishing the
dependence on
well we'll come down to different types
of wrong views in regards to the world
so how would one practically
relinquish views in regards to the world
relinquish dependencies on the Notions
of others and so on but what you
practically you need to do can you just
start thinking about those things and
relinquish them by figuring them out or
you do need to increase that certain
level of
withdrawal from certain things in the
same sense precepts we draw you from
certain unwholesome behaviors by body
and speech
yeah it seems to me that this desire for
gain and Renown and status on position
it's all bound up to itself view as well
like you know there's got to be a
self-image here or Emotional Self here
which then you know will and then there
will be others and then there's this
comparison better verse and all the rest
of it that's all kind of the result of
it but as I said in order to come to
that which is a problem what do you need
to give up
your household life
um in a way yeah more specifically so if
you or the lighting in company there you
go so basically the lighting company as
in
um but what does it mean to Delight yeah
we can get to that as well actually
because it doesn't just mean because
people can think oh Buddha said
seclusion and I'm always in seclusion
but the real reason is because I really
have your will towards everybody else
and it's like well that's not the
seclusion because you're not secluded
they will say the true seclusion like
the one dwells in company even when he's
alone if his mind is not free from greed
ill will and delusion
so
yes physical seclusion is necessary but
the reason why you do it is even more
necessary more important so physical
withdrawal not seeking company not
finding the lighting company
kind of yeah that would diminish you
referencing yourself from the point of
view of company and others uh you're
distracting yourself from the again
point of view of company what what other
things in regards to the world like this
how would you abandon concerns in regard
to the world what do you need to give up
what makes you concerned regarding the
entire world and people and so on
so you're talking about giving up
Central Behavior ill will
okay what else you do on the level of
your senses with the world how are you
engaging with the world
so through company
what are the things
information about it seeking exactly
yeah engaging with the level of
information news distraction views on the level of
news distraction views on the level of
ideals that pertain to regard to the
world the world better place all of that
needs to be abandoned just to begin Sati
patana rightly
because those are all factual concerns
there might not be a parent to somebody
who is also like crowded with sensuality
and household life and so on once you
withdraw yourself from that yeah that's
what the mind will revolve around those
are the underlying bases there and
that's why even like the when it will
describe the monk obviously with the
Right View says a skilled monk a noble
disciple abandons having been withdrawn
physically from these um
potentiality aversion ill will he
abandons thoughts of of sensuality
thoughts of Cruelty thoughts of harming
then he abandons uh like they're kind of
considered course then he also abandons
thoughts of his own like Clan hood and
Homeland and and basically on the level
of now that's where your conceit is who
you are in that broader sense so pretty
much concerning you know that the level
of the world as us humans he abandons
even those thoughts by again not by
denying them not by trying to get rid of
them but but okay I have those thoughts
now enduring in this mind well let me
establish the same context I was
established for when it came to
sensuality these thoughts lead to more
conceit more suffering more burden
Whenever there is identity where the
traces of identity or full-blown
identity duka will find the footing thus
by thinking these thoughts I am not
inclining this mind towards peace I'm
inclining it towards harm towards myself
towards others towards everything else
and and that's that so you have to give
up and you wouldn't be able to give up
these thoughts if you're still
in company about this spending your time
talking about politics and kings and
worlds and ministers as the suitors
would mention well we have the present
equivalent of that
reading news reading information keeping
in touch with with happenings even if
not necessarily you know political or
something but just oh in the world of
science in the world of Art in the world
in the world of full stop
means you still have certain connections
to it internally
and that's truly where the problem is
and for as long as those things are not
given up on that external level these
thoughts will not be seen for what they
are the subtle ones and even the duty
towards the family
I mean the whole point of the homeless
life was leaving it all behind
so like you know many monks would be
kind of all but it's still it's my duty
towards family my own family
so well to that extent you will not be
abandoning thoughts of your clients who
then and and belonging and cast and
wherever you come from because you are
still taking on that external duty of of
through which you're maintaining this
internal identity
it has to be I am alone in this world
for which I have no more happiness nor
concern and the reason that you would have no
and the reason that you would have no
more happiness or concern in regard to
the world is precisely because you would
see also this
for example you know if you get bothered
by
like war going on in the world or
poverty going on in the world or things
going on but you see what is the root
cause of any of those things create a
version delusion for example so if
you're taking if you see where that
problem is rightly in yourself you
couldn't be you could not be concerned
whatsoever with anything that goes on
with the world you're thinking that
seriously that is why you're concerned
with the world exactly because you are
because of those things that are root of
all these problems and concerns and
seeking the safety and so on
so that needs to be relinquished as well
is it uh obviously mundane
Right View and that wrong view that says
there is no mother there's no father
there's no world no next world no next
world there's nothing there's no given
you know it doesn't really exist see I'm
not identified with any of these things
that's right but that's actually the
wrong it's upside down yeah
there is mother there is fun there is
family and you have overcome the concern
in regard to it because you have denied
it or got rid of them or threw them out
like you would throw your possessions
and that's the point that's for me like
oh so you can't
throughout the world you can't throw out
your senses or well you can but you
would still equally be bound by those
domains by those Consciousness by you
you're not free
what you can do is overcome
that basis
for concern for last for a version for
this right for needing the safety
the base is basically that's that's
keeping you through your mind from being
liberated from it
but as I said
it's it's it roots are on the mental
level but in order to arrive at that
certain practical giving UPS need to be
done so like refining from seeking out
so like refining from seeking out
information
um
engaging discussing these things they're
like yeah but I mean I can but there's
no end to this and there's but they must
but why because you feel insecure and
unsafe well exactly does it come from
the world the lack of safety or does it
come from a mind that's not liberated
yeah you're making a choice there if you
act towards the world well
you got your answer you might claim that
you're still practicing for Liberation
you're not you you had the crossroads
and you perpetually keep choosing back
onto the world
and that's exactly how you would go
beyond the central domain not by
suppressing it so it doesn't come up
anymore nobody literally you stepping
out so you see it over there
and you see how safe you are because
that thing cannot not it can only be
over there and you know that
that's what it said like in the first
genre the thoughts are assailed by
perceptions of sensuality that you
basically withdrawn yourself from
because that's kind of what's in front
but you are outside now
so and sometimes there are
concerns to it that you know being
withdrawn from all these talks and
whatever May uh produce an impression on
others that you are avoiding them that
you are sort of hostile to them maybe
and and I mean even in monastic
environment Yeah so basically you have
to take it around as your responsibility
you have to accept it
because some people will probably see it
that way so you have to accept that yeah
well that's
and see that's why people would keep in
touch oh let's touch base let's just
keep seeing and talking to each other
every day so we all see that we are all
right because I mean we still might be
all right
but the fact that somebody's now
withdrawn from it the mind starts
thinking what if they are not all right
what if they're upset with me it's like
well yeah there is no end to that
proliferation the only ended up
proliferation is to recognize okay well
have I done anything my body speech in
mind to make them upset
no then okay then this mind that's
trying to make me go back there to make
sure nobody's upset with me I will
restrain I will re-establish context in
regard to it until those thoughts
subside all if upon reviewing Euros oh yeah no I
all if upon reviewing Euros oh yeah no I
did act a bit like this for a bit like
that well then go and apologize sort it
out but still do not use whether you
feel good or bad as a criteria whether
you should act but actually use your
reflection and see whether there was
anything done by Body speech towards
them to make them upset if not then you
got to endure the rational mind that's
trying to get you out of the solitude
and seek safety in your tribe and that's
that is so the the thoughts of oh What
will what will my peers what will my
clan what is my family what is my
brothers think of me
but those are the factual concerns it's
not like these random kind of abstract
thoughts that a skilled monk would have
no it's like on the level of sensuality
and ill will that now you're abandoned
well what took their place our thoughts
about who you are who you were how are they
who you are who you were how are they
see you
your past oh it's gonna have that same
weight and now you practice that right context
and now you practice that right context
in regard to it which means it's not
always going to be feel Pleasant in the
same sense practicing the context
against the you know I don't know
Central pull or acting out of a version
one people won't feel Pleasant
that's also quite directly related to
um being unable to see wholesome as
wholesome and unwholesomeness
unwholesome because what have measuring
your yourself what I should do or what I
shouldn't do did I act wrongly or not on
the level of
what do what will my clan my the people
I admire the people or whatever what
will they think of me uh is basically
what can in the beginning you might need to
can in the beginning you might need to
use the
um advice of wise people to send you in
a good direction but at some point you
need to be able to discern for yourself
what is acting wholesome what is acting
on wholesome and not depend on basically
and when you do those thoughts will
still come yes because that's what the
the Mind does but then it still has the
habits rooted in those subtly forms of
lust in aversion
uh but yeah if you have the right
reference you won't be acting out of how
those thoughts make you feel you won't
be acting out of doubt in other words
you would know better too no I gotta
endure this and re-establish the context
until subside on subsides on its own or
oh yeah no okay I should actually make
some effort externally sort the issues I
created and then go back to this either
way yeah
I remember one discussion with one monk
about it and well basically he was
referring to the Buddha himself talking
about having small talks basically when
somebody comes to him and they exchange
some uh greeting yeah pleasantries yeah
um so how how to so to understand where
is the limit to it so let's say the
reason behind
see they came started small talk for
another purpose so he met with so it's
like a way of expressing sort of
friendliness okay and then it would go
into a point so he wouldn't have a small
talk for the sake of distraction for the
sake of non-perspective for the sake of
Credo reversion
he wouldn't have the small talk for the
sake of carelessness
um so yeah that's what it is
maybe yeah maybe one can say and that
well um as long as one sees that this talks
um as long as one sees that this talks
really produce some uh who knows one
main thing is there as long as one
realize one is not the Buddha not even
in other hand one will not understand
how can arahan have a small dog so until
then maybe take the small talk seriously
in that sense do it only like as I said
as as like a as a way of relating to
others but not more nor less not make a
big deal out of it either
I wasn't talking to me in England angry
with everyone who tries who says good
morning to you or something uh but
fundamentally recognize yeah I don't
know where the line is because if I did
I would have the right View and be on
the verge of our hand chip and so on and
when I am then I'll figure out how can
the Buddha speak with Kings about you
know seemingly Pointless Stuff
um so there is that order of things
hmm so could the Criterion be in that as
so could the Criterion be in that as
long as I know that this sort of talks
is sort of unwholesome to me at least I
I should refrain from them if you know
what an awesome is like not not like oh
I don't like this that doesn't
necessarily mean it's unhealth I mean
let's say producing all these concerns
and I mean I say there are some and I
say innocent talk about politics I know yeah
yeah
no no sure yeah of course like if oh I
don't want my mind going there yeah yeah
you just you you're not you don't have
to talk to it and if people keep
insisting then you basically stop
associating with that it's as simple as
that because yeah you you know the general
because yeah you you know the general
household life that those are the
factual real life concerns and they
should not pertain that's where like you
know even like in the suit is you know
when monks like we sort of put put each
other down they would say like ah you
can't take him seriously he's intimate
with householders he has householders
for his friends means he's not a proper
monk that's all he took having
householders is your friends because you
kind of share their concerns by
implication uh but then there were cases of arahants
uh but then there were cases of arahants
having householders for the friends
so in and of itself as I said that's not
what the root of the problem is but most
practically for most people yeah that
has to be restrained until you actually
approved it and then to what extent
you'll engage in those talks afterwards
you'll see but it won't be done for the
sake of distraction or whatever else or
out of C like I don't really care about
the politics but I care what others
think about me and now they want to talk
politics and if I don't politics they'll
think bad about me so I'll talk politics
or whatever they want to talk well
that's equally and wholesome
so I'm acting out of that weakness no I
need to take on the weight yeah they
might talk badly about me behind my back
that's fine and that's part of
relinquishing my concern uh my conceit
defined by others it's not going to be
pleasant because it was something you
accrued and and live by
so it's it's who you are pretty much